A Guide to the Moses Kunitz papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA171
Rockefeller Archive Center
Moses Kunitz papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1913-1970
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Kunitz, Moses
FA171
8.8 Cubic Feet
12 boxes, 1 package; 1 tube package, 2 volumes
Biographical/Historical note
Moses Kunitz, 1887-1978 researcher in general pathology and biochemistry worked on the physical and chemical properties of proteins and enzymes at the Rockefeller University (earlier RIMR) from 1913 until his retirement in 1970. His research covered the purification and crystallization of a. number of very important enzymes which take part in forming and utilizing energy-rich compounds within the body.
Biographical note
1887 Born December 19 in Slonim, Russia
1909 Migrated to the United States
1916 B.S. Cooper Union, New York City (1910 entered School of Chemistry)
1916-1919 Cooper Union Electrical Engineering School
1919 Extension Teaching Columbia University, New York City
1920 School of Mines, Engineering and Chemistry, Columbia Univ.
1922 Faculty of Pure Science, Columbia University
1924 Ph. D. Columbia University, New York City (Biological Chemistry)
1913-1923 Technical Assistant, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Worked with Jacques Loeb in experimental biology. From 1926 with John Northrop at Princeton laboratories
1923-1925 Assistant, RIMR (General Physiology)
1925-1940 Associate, RIMR (General Physiology)
1944 Civilian with Office of Scientific Research and Development
1950-1953 Member, RIMR
1953- Member Emeritus, RIMR
1957 Carl Neuberg Medal (American Society of European Chemists & Pharmacists)
1970 Retired from The Rockefeller University
1973 Honorary Degree, RU, New York City
1978 Died April 20 in Philadelphia, Pa. Interred Wellwood Cemetery on Long Island, N.Y.
Member of: National Academy of Sciences, American Association for the Advancement of Science, Society for Experimental Biology, Society of General Physiologists, American Society of Biological Chemists
Arrangement note
Arranged in chronological order within subject.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 K962
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Dates received or inventoried: 1970, 1974, 1978, 1984. All received or inventoried in 1970, 1974, or 1978 unless otherwise noted.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: biographical material, notes, slides, photographs, reprints, and memorabilia.
Pathology; Proteins -- Synthesis; Medicine, Preventive; Biology -- Research; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Chemistry; Medical education; Medical research; Proteins; Medical sciences; Diseases; Prevention and health; Biochemistry
- Biographical material (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Photograph, bibliography, obituary notice Honorary Degree citation.
- Crystal preparation (Box 1)
  3 letters: Greene, Lewis J.; Schmid, Karl; Stern, Herbert.
- Student notebooks, 3 folders (Box 1)
  11 notebooks of course material from Cooper Union and from Columbia.
- Laboratory notes and records
  - Laboratory procedures, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Gelatin, alcohol and salt ppt, 1920-1921 (Box 2)
  - Gelatin, viscosity, O.P., P.D., 1921-1922 (Box 2)
  - Gelatin, swelling-diffusion potentials, 1921-1927 (Box 2)
  - Egg albumin, 1921 (Box 2)
  - Conductivity 1920; Electrical endomosis 1921-1922, 1920, 1921-1922 (Box 2)
  - Casein, 1921 1923-1924 (Box 2)
  - Cataphoresis, 1922-1923; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Ion combination, 1924-1925 (Box 3)
  - Isoelectric gelatin, 1925-1929 (Box 3)
  - Diffusion gelatin 1930; Diffusion experiments 1934-1951, 1930 1934-1951 (Box 3)
  - Trypsin, 1931-1932 (Box 3)
  - Laboratory notes and records (Box 4)
  - Tsin denaturation 1932-1933; Inactivation of Tsin 1933 (Box 4)
  - Chymatgen; Trypsinogen, 1933 (Box 4)
  - Degamma; Activation by Enterokinase, 1933 (Box 4)
  - Trypsin 1934-1935; Activation of Trypsinogen 1934-1937, 1934 1935-1937 (Box 4)
  - Trypsin-pancreatic inhibitor compound 1938 (Box 4)
  - Chymotrypsin, 1936-1937 1937-1938; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Mold kinase, 1937 (Box 5)
  - Thromboplastin; Enterokinase, 1938 (Box 5)
  - Ribonuclease, 1939-1940 1945-1946 (Box 5)
  - Hexokinase, 1941-1942 1943; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Absorption spectra data, 1944-1951 (Box 5)
  - Soybean denaturation 1945-1946; Soybean inhibitor 1946 (Box 5)
  - B. Brodsky notebook, no. 4, 1945 (Box 5)
  - Desoxyribonuclease, 1946-1948 1949-1950; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Nucleo-proteins, 1948 1949 1949-1950; 3 folders (Box 6)
    Including 1970 January 1 letter from Vincent Allfrey commenting "very first to employ nucleases and proteases in study of histone-DNA interaction".
  - Cu Phenal 1950; Pyrophosphatase (Box 6)
  - Pyrophosphatase, 1951 (Box 6)
  - Invertase, 1951 1952-1953 1961; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Yeast phosphatase, 1953 1953-1954 1954 1954-1955; 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Yeast phosphatase, 1955-1956 (Box 8)
  - Intestinal phosphatase - preparation, 1957-1958 (Box 8)
  - Intestinal phosphatase (chicken), 1957-1959 (Box 8)
    Material for publication and calculations.
  - Intestinal phosphatase: references, charts, tables, rough draft (Box 8)
  - Laboratory log books, 7 items (Box 8)
    - Beckman Spectrophotometer, 1959
    - Zwischenferment, 1958-1959
    - Isolation of Zwischenferment, 1960
    - Zwischenferment, 1961
    - Zwischenferment, 1962
    - Isolation of pyrophosphatase, 1960-1961
    - Isolation of Asparaginase, 1961-1962
  - Yeast (Bakers and Brewers), 1957-1959 (Box 9)
  - Yeast asparaginase, 1961-1964 January (Box 9)
  - Yeast experiments (Alan Absgarten notes), 1962-1963 (Box 9)
  - Potato phosphatase, 1959-1960 1960-1961 1963 1964-1965; 3 folders (Box 9)
- Laboratory notes and records, 1965-1966 1967-1970; 2 folders (Box 10)
  Potato phosphatase.
- Lantern slides, 3¼ × 4 inch (Box 11)
  Graphs and charts and photographs of crystals.
- Laboratory photographs (Box 12)
  - untitled, 30 glass plates; negatives; prints; 2 color negatives
  - Original drawings of illustrations used in publications Unidentified, 1 folder
    Journal of General Physiology: v. 18, no. 3; v. 19, no. 6; v. 21, no. 5; v. 22, no. 2; v. 24, no. 1; v. 25, no. 1; v. 29, no. 3; v. 29, no. 6; v. 30, no. 4; v. 32, no. 1; v. 33, no. 4; v. 35, no. 3.
- Original drawings of illustrations used in publications, 12 × 14¾ × ½" (oversize) (Box 1 pkg.)
  Journal of General Physiology: v. 23,no. 3; v. 43,no. 6; v. 45,no. 4.
- Certificate of membership in National Academy of Sciences, 2¾ × 17½" (Box 1 tube pkg.)
- Collected Reprints, 1923-1970; 2 volumes
  Separated Materials
  Removed to RAC Library
- Photographs of Moses Kunitz, group photographs at Princeton and of Princeton Staff and Rockefeller Institute views (Box 13, Folder 1)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Received by the Rockefeller University Archives, November 1984, from Mrs. Roslyn Albert (Dr. Kunitz's daughter) via Professor Emeritus William Trager.
  - Moses Kunitz, Early undated; 2 × 2 print
  - Princeton laboratory photograph of M.L. Anson, R.M. Herriott, J.H. Northrop, V. Desreaux and M. Kunitz, 1939
  - Princeton laboratory photograph of M. Kunitz, M.L. Anson, J.H. Northrop, unidentified, undated
  - RIMR, Princeton Staff group photograph. See photo for some identification, undated
  - RIMR, Princeton Staff group photograph, 1942
  - RIMR, Princeton Staff group photograph, 1947
  - Photographs, undated
    M. Kunitz in Dining Room, Welch Hall with Dr. Tsao?.
    M. Kunitz with William Trager.
    M. Kunitz. Official portrait.
  - RI Hospital with hospital addition, 1950
  - RI Campus from East River with Hospital addition, 1950
- Photographs of others (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Various photographs of Mortimer L. Anson. One with Kreuger, undated
  - Simon Flexner, at Woods Hole, Mass. Carrying books under left arm, 1923
  - Jacques Loeb. Photo by Louis Schmidt, 1923
  - At Woods Hole?, undated
    Includes.
    - Jacques Loeb
    - Jacques Loeb and Brandes
    - Parking area at Marine Biological Laboratories, Woods Hole, Mass
    - Leo Loeb at microscope, undated
    - Leonor Michaelis. Official portrait, undated
    - Assorted prints, undated
      Some identified.
      Includes: David Hitchcock; Dr. Lilly; Thomas Moore; Dr. Parker; Dr. Chambers is one of three on photograph; The Worthingtons.
      Remaining photographs unidentified.
- Hans Neurath reprint with inscription. "To Moses Kunitz who started it all, with the best wishes, " January 1965, signed Hans Neurath. On 1964 Dec reprint. Hans Neurath, "Protein-digesting Enzymes". Science 211 (1964) 68-78, 1964 December-1965 January (Box 13, Folder 3)
- re: William Trager (Box 13, Folder 4)
  These items appear to have been sent to Mrs. R. Albert by William Trager, July 27, 1976.
  - Printed leaflet contains professional and biographical information and Principle Contributions to Science by William Trager
  - New York Times, "Hope Rises for Vaccine Against Malaria". News clipping, 1976 June 1
- Laboratory notes, bibliography and reprints, 2½" (Box 14)
  - Bound alphabetical record book of subject lab notes primarily reference for chemical compounds and scientific equivalents (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Laboratory notebooks, 2 items (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Potato acid phosphatase (crystals), 1968 October-1969 April
    - Potato acid phosphatase. Wheat germ, 1968-1971
  - Laboratory notes (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Asparaginas, 1962
    - Potatoe-acid phosphatase, 1970-1971
  - Kunitz, Moses bibliography, 1923-1962 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Reprints. Kunitz et al reprints (Box 14, Folder 5)
    Includes J.H. Northrop reprint with inscription to Kunitz.
  - Margaret McDonald lab notes on ribonuclease, 1948 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    [Found in Kunitz volume of collected reprints 1932-1948. #15. McDonald reprint.].
- Memorabilia, 5" (Box 15)
  - Academic Robe
  - Carl Neuberg Medal
    Awarded to Moses Kunitz, 3 April 1957, Hunter College, New York City, American Society of European Chemists and Pharmacists Carl Neuberg Medal Meeting. From Printed Program in Medal case: Fritz Lipmann, "Greetings to Moses Kunitz." Roger M. Herriott, "Moses Kunitz: The Man and His Contributions to Science".
  - Mounted membership certificate
  - Moses Kunitz, Class of 1915, 1915-1965 June 9
  - Golden Legion Membership Certificate, Mounted
    Awarded by this Cooper Union Alumni organization whose members have made significant contributions to their professions.
  - A calendar page with following written on it " U J A 8 p.m. 220 W 58", 1932-1948 1968 February 28
    [Found in Kunitz collected reprints 1932-1948 (bound volume) with #15 reprint, p. 40 of M.R. McDonald reprint.
- M. Kunitz Collected Reprints, 2 volumes
  - Volume 1a, 1924-1931
  - Volume 2a, 1932-1948
- Charts from Moses Kunitz's office, oversize (Package #3)
  Given and identified by Prof. Paul Cranefield.
  Ammonium sulfate concentration table.
  Graph from L. Michaelis book.
- Honorary doctorate from RU, 1973; tube (Package #4)